Guide to the John Hart Ely Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Inventory, 1833-2003
  - Research background files
    - Cambodia
      - Press coverage of bombing, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Campaign finance, 1997-1998 (Box 9, Folder 18-22)
    - Central Intelligence Agency (CIA)
      - General, 1994-1996 (Box 9, Folder 23)
      - War Powers Resolution (WPR), 1985 (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Secret funding of CIA, etc., constitutionality of, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Clinton and war powers, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Covert war, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Cuba, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Defense budget, 1992-1994 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Dellums and Ange complaints, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Draft, Undated (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Eisenhower, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Emergency powers, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Executive's domestic powers in wartime, Undated (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - War of the future, 1988-1992 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Gays in the military, 1993-1997 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - Haiti, 1993-1994 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Intelligence budget, secrecy of, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - International law (general), Undated (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - VNA: international law, Undated (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Isolationism article, 1965-1990 (Box 9, Folder 41-42)
    - JFK and withdrawal from Viet Nam (Vietnam), 1992 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - Korea, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - Kuwait, etc., 1990-1991 (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - Laos
      - Coverage elsewhere than New York Times, 1964-1989 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      - New York Times coverage, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 47)
      - Economist 's coverage, 1962-1969 (Box 9, Folder 48)
      - Washington Post and UPI (United Press International) on start of bombing, 1964 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Latin America, US military intervention in, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Military as cautious on military involvement [in Middle East], 1990 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - MIAs (soldiers missing in action), 1992-1996 (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Murder programs, US involvement in (Indonesia), 1990 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Control over National Guard, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Nuclear war, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Eliminating nuclear capacity of other countries, Undated (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Pacificism, 1963-1985 (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Peacetime development of forces, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Persian Gulf naval war, 1987-1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Poems, anti-war, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Practice, outline concerning, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - POWs/MIAs (prisoners of war/missing in action), 1995 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Rosenbergs, 1977-1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Secrecy in government, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Somalia, Circa 1995 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - State action, 1979-1986 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Strategic Defense Initiative (SDI), 1983-1992 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Speeches on war, 1988-1995 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Term limits, 1991-1997 (Box 10, Folder 11-12)
    - Terrorism, war on, 2001-2002 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Bush's anti-terror programs, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - Treasure, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Tribe, Laurence H., 1986-2000 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - Talks concerning war, Undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - Troxel piece: SDP (substantive due process) parental rights, 1973-2000 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Treason, Undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Treaties, mutual cooperation and security, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - "U.N. (United Nations) charter as authorization" argument, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - UN as war-authorized, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 22)
    - Utilitarianism
      - Democracy, utilitarianism, and judicial review: overall outlines, Circa 1981 (Box 10, Folder 23)
      - I. Why Democracy?, 1981-1983 (Box 10, Folder 24)
      - II. Democracy as applied utilitarianism, Undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - III. Critiques of utilitarianism, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - IV. Critiques of way system operates, Undated (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - Problems with the utilitarian-democratic translation (including personal-external preferences), 1981 (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - V. Judicial review as response to defects in applied utilitarianism, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 29)
      - Intensity and democracy, Circa 1982 (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - Intensity piece, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 31)
      - Equality and democracy piece (bumped by Dworkin piece), 1983 (Box 10, Folder 32)
      - Dworkin's writings, Undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
      - Articles, book chapters, and notes: arranged by author's name
        - A, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 34)
        - B, 1965-1973 (Box 10, Folder 35)
        - C, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 36)
        - D, Undated (Box 10, Folder 37)
        - F, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 38)
        - G, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 39)
        - H, 1967-1985 (Box 10, Folder 40)
        - K, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - L, 1956-1977 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
        - M, 1962-1980 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - N-O, 1971, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - P, 1970-1979 (Box 11, Folder 6-8)
        - R, 1965-1984 (Box 11, Folder 9-10)
        - S-W, 1930-1981 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
    - Vietnam
      - VNA: what actions need congressional approval? (scope), 1990 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - VNB: "overall" outlines and ideas, 1986-1990 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - War and democracy, 1995 May-June (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - War and Responsibility
      - Second edition, 1991-1995 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Reviews, 1993-1995 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Typos to be corrected, 1993-1994 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - War powers
      - Post-book, 1991-2001 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence with Dellinger re: U.S. forces deployment to Haiti, 1994-1995 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - War and women: think piece, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Wealth disparity, 1995 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Welfare, 1997 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - HHW (Harry H. Wellington) talk, New York Law School, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Women's role: 1992 election and choice (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Yoo, John, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Reviews and notes
    Arrangement
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Abrams-Atwood, 1954-1992 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Bailyn-Bestor, 1920-1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Bickel-Bronner, 1948-1990 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Calhoun-Cooperstein, 1953-1990 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Corwin-Crovitz, 1914-1990 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Dahl-Dyer, 1957-1984 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Eagleton-Emerson, 1938-1977 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Fairman-Fuller, 1937-1992 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Gaddis-Gunther, 1938-1991 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Halberston-Hyman, 1909, 1968-1990 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Ides-Isaacson, 1984-1992 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Javits-Jurrow, 1929-1989 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Kahin-Kunland, 1956-1992 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Lafeber-Lyons, 1962-1990 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - MacPherson-Maurice, 1962-1990 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Mayo-Moynihan, 1933-1991 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Nagel-Note, 1968-1991 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Ono-O'Toole, 1965-1991 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Paige-Purcell, 1955-1990 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Ratner-Rutland, 1953-1991 (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Sanford-Smyrl, 1964-1992 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Sofaer-Szuls, 1833-1988 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Tenbroek-Tushnet, 1909-1975 (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - Unger, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Warren-Wright, 1923-1978 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Drafts of articles and reviews, and feedback
    - Feedback regarding: Roe piece, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Feedback on "motive" piece, 1970-1981 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Harris and Wyman piece: drafts, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Harris piece: feedback, 1971, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Early drafts of Roe piece, 1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Sex as suspect classification, 1971 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Early drafts of Erie piece, Circa 1973 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Feedback on Erie piece, 1974-1980 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - DeFunis piece
      General
      Case deals with racial discrimination.
      - Early drafts, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Feedback, 1974-1975 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Warren tribute
      - Early drafts, Undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Feedback, Undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Lovett piece: early draft, feedback, 1963-1976 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      Scope and Contents
      The article deals with separation of powers.
    - Warren Commission op-ed piece, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Flag piece
      - First drafts, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Feedback, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Busing: op-ed, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Readers' reports, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Lectures: Indiana, Maryland, Samuel Fox Mordecai, 1978, undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Indiana, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 20)
      - Feedback, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Maryland, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 22)
      - Feedback, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 23)
    - United States Constitution paper, Undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
      Article written in response to one by Professor Murphy.
    - San Diego Law Review: motivation analysis, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - Feedback on Foreward ( Harvard Law Review ), 1979 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - Feedback on book, 1959, 1978-1983 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - AEI paper, 1982, undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Abortion: op-ed piece, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 29)
    - New York University (NYU) paper: "Democracy and the Right to be Different", 1981 (Box 13, Folder 30)
    - "On Constitutional Nihilism", 1981 (Box 13, Folder 31)
    - Conflicts
      - Drafts: "Choice of Law and the State's Interest in Protecting Its Own" and "Interest Analysis and 'False Conflicts': Will Understanding Our Problems Really Make Them Go Away?", 1981, undated (Box 13, Folder 32-34)
      - Feedback, 1982, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Talk, Undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Tresolini lecture notes, Undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - "The New Attainder - of Form and Function", Circa 1963 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Dworkin piece: drafts, 1983-1984 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      Includes feedback on article.
    - Feedback on New Republic piece, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Shapiro piece (and Yale Law Journal celebration), 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - University of Virginia piece
      - Drafts, 1976-1991 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Feedback, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Article on David Hume: drafts and correspondence, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Letter to New York Times regarding: creche case, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Motive and constitutional law: draft research papers, Undated (Box 14, Folder 12-15)
    - Interview notes and correspondence, 1966, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - Free Press article, 1966 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - Congressional privilege: draft opinion article, Undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - Book of things, Undated (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Donald Stewart, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Ideas for fiction; places to publish?, Undated (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Possible non-legal articles, 1995, undated (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - National Security Agency NSA, etc., 1976-1983 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Stewardesses, 1986 June (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Doctors
      - Attitudes, Undated (Box 14, Folder 25)
      - Waiting for, Undated (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Fiction by others, 2001 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    - History/philosophy, "humorous", Undated (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Line of succession, 1979, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 29)
    - Princeton article
      - Drafts, etc., 1985-1990 (Box 14, Folder 30)
      - Piece, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - Public defender files and court clerk materials
    - California State Superior Court: reporter's partial transcript, California v. Robert Gonzalez, 1968 May 24 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      Ely acted for the defense.
    - Municipal Court, San Diego Judicial District: California v. James Sullivan, preliminary hearing, 1968 March 14-15 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - State of California, Fourth Appellate District
      - California v. Frank White, reporters' transcript, 1968 May 1-8 (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
      - Kenneth Sanberg v. California, writ of prohibition, 1968 May (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - United States District Court
      - Southern California
        - United States of America (USA) v. Edward Wilson, Jeffrey Herwitz, 1967 July 26-27 (Box 15, Folder 6)
        - USA v. Apolonio Gomez-Vazquez, 1967 April 12 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - District of Columbia: Ronald Delmus v. George Bush, amicus curiae brief and civil action opinion, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - United States Court of Appeals, Ninth Circuit
      - Billy Joe Martin v. USA: appellant's brief and reply brief, 1968 March-May (Box 15, Folder 9)
      - Oscar John Huguez v. USA: appellant's brief and reply brief, 1967 (Box 15, Folder 10)
      - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee v. Janet Reno, amicus curiae brief, 1994 October 7 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - United States Supreme Court
      - Billy Joe Martin v. USA, 1968 August-October (Box 15, Folder 12-13)
      - Clippings regarding: opinions, 1965-1968 (Box 15, Folder 14)
      - Kent v. USA (Justice Warren's dissent); Roscoe Barrow, 1965 March 2, undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
      - Drews v. Maryland, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 16)
      - Hanna v. Plumer, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 17)
      - Udall v. Tallman, 1964-1965 (Box 15, Folder 18)
      - Zemel v. Rusk, 1965 March-May (Box 15, Folder 19)
      - USA v. Brown, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Opinions in cases handled (published), 1968-1969 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Federal Defenders, Inc. (FDI) memos, 1966-1968 (Box 15, Folder 22-23)
    - Gray Cary memos (antitrust, contracts), 1963 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Neighborhood Legal Services Program (NLSP) evaluation, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - Rex v. Preston, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    Moot court presentation of 1770 Boston Massacre case, filmed for Georgia Educational Television Network.
  - United States Department of Transportation (USDOT) files
    - v. Environmental Defense Fund regarding: Concorde
      - Notes and briefs, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Court briefs and proceedings, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 2)
      - 1975 Aviation Act, USDOT statements, and media coverage transcripts, 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 3)
      - Congressional hearings on environmental impact of supersonic travel, 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Memorandum regarding: Concorde opinion, 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
      - Oversight hearings on National Environmental Policy Act: notes and transcripts, 1974-1975 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - Intervention briefs, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 8-9)
      - Environmental Defense Fund v. USDOT and USDOT documents concerning Concorde litigation, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Ely scrapbook: USDOT correspondence, media releases, news clippings, personal photos and memorabilia, 1975-1976 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Views of Saipan service and railroad regulations, 1976 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Video recordings
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Boston Massacre Trial [commercially produced]
      - Part I, 1976 December 14; 1 (Box 17)
        - Use copy, 1 (Box 17U)
      - Part II, 1976 December 14; 1 (Box 18)
        - Use copy, 1 (Box 18U)
    - Jimmy Carter, Ralston Lecture, Kresge Auditorium, 1987 March 10; 1 (Box 19)
    - C-SPAN State Department [commercially produced], 1994 July 13; 1 (Box 20)
    - Currie Lecture, Duke Law School [commercially produced], 1973; 1 (Box 21)
    - The Landing of the Concorde - SST at Kennedy [commercially produced]
      - Tape 1, 1976 February 25; 1 (Box 22)
      - Tape 2, 1976 February 25; 1 (Box 23)
    - Law Review War Powers Symposium, Room 109, 1995 February 24; 4 (Box 24–27)
    - Massachusetts School of Law Educational Forum: The War Power [commercially produced]
      - Show #39, Part 1, Undated; 1 (Box 28)
      - Show #40, Part 2, Undated; 1 (Box 29)
    - Ras Mohamed: John Ely with Iman, 1998 February 7; 1 (Box 30)
    - Remembering Slavery, Ira Berlin (ed.), Undated; 1 (Box 31)
- Additional Material, 1974-circa 2001; Accession 2012-M-023
  The computer files are closed until processed.
  - Research paper: The Consitutionality of "Benign" Racial Discrimination, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General counsel, U.S. Department of Transportation, confirmation hearing prep materials and correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Edited research paper: Judicial Review of Suspicious Classifications: Why is Classification by Race "Suspect," and Should Classification by Sex Similarly be Subjected to Extraordinary Scrutiny?, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Computer files, Circa 1989-2001 (Box 2–5)
    The materials include writings, course materials and correspondence on 158 5.25" computer disks.